[Music]
we were discussing a variety of
manifolds which were made by operations
product quotient and
surgery starting from building blocks
and there is one more example that I
like
to discuss which we'll
use and that is this funny
example as usual let's take a square and
then thinking of it as a an elastic
sheet or piece of
paper let's ask ourselves what happens
if I identify this Edge and this Edge
like so up and
down and this Edge
and this is in the opposite direction as
well I'd like to remind you that if we
had this same direction here and here
you get a manifold called clim
botle
yeah and if we had the same direction
here and same direction here you get the
TOs but now we have the opposite
direction vertically and opposite
direction horizontally also so what is
this object now
this object is difficult to
visualize so let us try to figure out
what this looks like by calculating with
pictures
here is how we shall
calculate we start from
this keeping track of how the
identifications
go
and
hi I cut it along
this curve I cut the whole thing along
this curve naturally after I cut it at
the end I have to glue them back
together otherwise it's not going to be
the same thing but when I cut it I get
two p is as a
result wow that falling apart for some
reason this piece and this piece yeah
and let's keep marking the
identification arrows like this at the
end as we say we have to identify glue
back together the cuts so let's keep
track of them by putting those marks do
you understand why I put them in the
same direction because they must be
glued together not the other era yeah
okay now the top piece is not difficult
to see what it
is I'll keep using yellow if you
like
oops like that and like that let's focus
on the vertical
edges not worrying at the moment about
the horizontal ones but as far as the
vertical Edge is concerned you can see
what happens you can take this twist and
glue it's the mov
stre can you draw pictures as fast as I
I'm
doing difficult huh but that's how oh
wait a minute so having bragged about
this I think it should probably look
like this and then you should look like
this it should look like this and that
piece came like that and because I
twisted upside down it looks like that
and then
this comes in like that this comes in
like that and then this is like this and
this is like this okay so if I glue them
together identify the vertical strips I
get the standard movie strip so far so
good
and then you get this in the back you
get this in front and somewhere in the
middle um there's an interesting that
thing that happens um so this is that
but this is this so in the middle those
marks exchange
places what about the bottom the bottom
piece is also easy to visualize because
we're doing
topology this half of this
I can stretch it and make it into a full
dis so this point and this point those
Corners became those two points but the
rest is the
same topologically the same thing as the
semi
disk so what we are doing what we have
to do is the following
operation you see there's a this disk
whose boundary
consists of a single Circle single
Circle which is marked by this solid
Arrow followed by this sort of rounded
Arrow if you look at the M strip we know
that it's boundary is also a single
Circle and if you go along the boundary
you get this solid
Arrow followed by the round Arrow so
it's exactly the same boundary what we
have to do then is to glue this to this
piece along the boundaries along common
boundaries
thus what we
have Excuse
me yes some
people ah okay so you dro the pen
okay sometimes I lecture so fast that a
student said that he dropped a pen bent
over to pick it up and because of this
missed all of complex
analysis so this is the same as the
movie
strip and you take a dis I'm drawing the
disc a bit sideways okay and
then glue the boundaries together so
heis
St and the
dis and
identify them
along the their boundary
circles that is slightly better that's a
little easier to visual than in the
beginning but it's still quite difficult
to visualize what do we get if I take a
dis and along the circular boundary I
glue the boundary of movies St you
cannot do this in 3D by the way
difficult to visualize but let's argue
as follows you know this disc that we
have I draw a Caron picture there now
putting horizontally suppose that I push
up the edge a little bit and make it
into this shape
yeah that's still topologically a dis
it's the same thing homeomorphic to a
dis you can see that and then just keep
stretching
this and eventually I get a shape like
this which is a sphere with one hole
drilled out that shape sphere minus a
disk is still homeomorphic to a
dis okay so we can in fact visualize
this as follows instead of this let's
take a sphere with the hold drill
out
now the boundary that you see is a
circle and you can try to let's see that
let's see how we can close this hole the
usual way to close this hole is to take
a disc and put it on as a lid that's
possible partically because the boundary
of the dis is a circle so I can identify
the circle with this circle I can glue
it along the circle but let's imagine I
want you to exercise your imagination
that I take a mov
strip and glue the circular boundary of
the movie strip along this circular
boundary that's another way of closing
this
hole again it's impossible to do in 3D
but you can do this
so drill a
hole on a
sphere and put a Le
on with a M
stream this is what results if you make
those identifications that we're
discussing um in the beginning we will
draw this
[Applause]
result
as well there's no good way to draw it
so I shall take a very simple draw
picture I'm going to put a circle and
then put something like
this so whenever you see this picture it
means dra out a
hole but put a lid back on not with the
ordinary lead but with a movie strip
glue back a movie strip on the hole and
the result is drawn like this okay and
this resulting
surface closed surface mind you is
called
the
real projective plane there was the
still is a beautiful area of geometry
called projective
geometry which was organized in the 19
century and the projective plane is
where the projective geometry takes
place real because there's something
called complex projective plane which I
shall not um discuss we shall not
discuss in this course and the notation
for this which we shall use is RP 2 R
because it's real P stands for
projective and two because it's two
dimensional it's a surface
okay difficult to visualize but that's
what it is we shall use this object a
number of times like and we'll
eventually get used to this
okay we have discussed two operations
product and quotient so to speak
multiplication and division now we'll
discuss the third and most interesting
of those operations which will name
surgery it is a little like addition and
subtraction you cut and
paste various
manifolds here is the definition
of how to cut and
paste let's say that you have two
manifolds MF LD stands for
manifold M1 M2 over the same
Dimension let's call it small
M so the picture that I have in mind
is so I don't know what's happening to
this manifold on this side but here you
get a manifold like this so that's M1
yeah it might be very
complicated and another
manifold again I don't know what's
what's beyond there but that's
M2
okay what we shall do and these both
have the same Dimension M what we shall
both what we shall do is to drill out a
hole from
here remove this this
thing when I say a hole on a Surface
Dimension two surface a hole is a two
dimensional ball disc on an M
dimensional manifold a hole is an M
dimensional Ball by the way if you have
a onedimensional curve that's one
dimensional manifold if you make a hole
what you get you get a one ball which is
just an interval okay so when I say a
hole I mean
[Music]
so an UL so I'm going to take away this
kind of thing and also I'm going to make
another hole on the other side as
well so hands of God are taking away
these
things so this is in the old not in the
familiar notation a ball of Dimension M
but I'm going to say that it's B1
because it was taken away from M1 and
this is B2 because it was taken away
from M2 so given those two manifolds
remove an
emble from each
manifold so drill a
hole and then I'm going
having removed those how are those what
do those pictures look
like
M1
M2 identify
the boundaries of the
holes okay and the resulting surface
will the cartoon picture look like
this and this is where theyve been glued
together so that's that was used to be
M1 that used to be M2
yeah the result in fact it's a quotient
space under this
unification is you know how to write
this kind of thing so
M1 you take away a ball so what remains
this thing looks like looks like this in
fact and then on the other side you have
M2 you took away a ball from that what
it looks like is this so you take this
manifold and then you take the quotient
you make the identification and what is
the identification I have to identify
this with this that's what we mean by
gluing these two things together and
formally what it means is that you take
the boundary of this
manifold this boundary is precisely this
and then boundary of
the other piece
this is that and then glue them together
so you want to identify those two things
so this is what it is and this is
denoted Always by M1 M2 with what in
English is called a hash sign and
that's called the connected
sum very strange name connected some
anyway of M1 and M2
I have just defined the operation of
surgery or connected some so if you have
any two manifolds of the same Dimension
you can take their connected some you
can glue them together but how do we
mean glue them together precisely we
mean you take a hole you make a hole on
one side or you make the hole on the
other side and then put the holes
together and that's what happens in the
connected sound
okay okay let's see some examples
of connected Sun example 14 oh the Sun
is going in that's bad okay question
what is the connected sum the simplest
case of S1 and S1 do you remember what
S1 is
yes it's a not a sphere one dimensional
sphere but the more common name is a
circle what do you think the connected
sum of S1 and S1 is
let's play The Honest Game then so
that's one this one that's another S one
what do we have to do we have to take
away a hole what do we mean by hole
where we make a hole we take away a
onedimensional ball which is an
interval yeah so we took this away we
took this
away and then now we have to
identify the boundaries of those holes
so what you going to
get well you going to get something like
this it's a
curve but that's of course homeomorphic
to to
this so the
answer is that piz again
S1 so connected sum of S1 and S1 is just
S1 that's very
easy
okay this is quite easy but it's a
little surprising we were perhaps
expecting that we get something new by
connecting some S1 and S1 so in a way S1
in this case behaved like
zero yeah 0 + 0 is 0 for no other number
do you have the property that that
number plus that number is the same
number so here is a imediate interesting
question what plays the role of
zero for the operation of connected
some
namely what
manifold let's say Zed has the
property that Z connected some with some
other manifold is again the same
manifold yeah we can ask that
question hm S1 yeah S1 S1 but you see S1
is used in the connected sum in one
dimension if you are connecting some say
two uh so two dimensional manif for you
have to S2 if you do it in 3D S3 and so
on good you have a very good nose um
congratulations to
Egypt so the ser
is that indeed spheres play the role of
zero with respect to the connected
sum so for every
manifold M of
Dimension M it is a case that s m
connect Su with m is again equal to
M and the proof
is obvious but it's nice to see how
obvious it is here's how it
goes let's say that you have this
strange M and it can be a complicated
manifold and you have a sphere I'm going
to draw two dimensional
pictures what do I do I drill out the
hole
here and then I drill out the hole here
yeah and then I glue those boundaries
together and what I'm going to get well
I'm going to
get something like
this this was m and this was the
sphere yeah but you see this is
ballooning out but I can shrink it and
then I can gently push it down and it's
exactly the same thing as
the original did somebody sneeze in that
case bless
you the original and that's what
true if you're a little nervous you can
also argue as follows you see here I
removed an M dimensional
ball I'm going to glue
back this sphere minus an M dimensional
bow but sphere minus an M dimensional
hole is in fact also an M dimensional
hole and you can see it in the following
case in 2D imagine a sphere and think of
it as consistent of north northern
hemisphere and southern
hemisphere removing a little bit of hole
from the Arctic Antarctica excuse me you
get a sphere with a hole at the bottom
but that's the same thing as if you like
just by making that hole larger and
larger just the northern hemisphere
which is the same thing as if you flat
on the Northern Hemisphere just an
equatorial dis so in fact what you are
gluing from left is just a dis I removed
a dis I glued back the dis the result
doesn't change so that's the zero
element end of
proof
okay please however be careful not
everything is so
trivial a common mistake made by almost
all
beginners is in what you are removing in
order to do the connected sound you must
remove a single ball from each
side
[Applause]
so please be careful that in Connected
Su you remove
a sing only
one
ball from each
side an example to show that it is
important let's say that you want to
consider the connect sum of a
Taurus and a
sphere but suppose that you are careless
and instead of removing one hole and one
hole here I removed two holes here and
two holes
there okay two holes and then I identify
the holes what are you going to get as a
result you can probably visualize this
right what you're going to get is
something like
this and that is of course the same same
thing
as a donut with two holes you see the
result is not the same thing as the
Taurus it changed although we seem to be
adding a sphere contrary to what we said
sphere does not play the role of zero
aha but that's because we did not do the
connected sum connected sum takes only
one hole away from each and glue this is
taking two from each that's illegal
okay so this is
not how you
make S2
and T2 connected sum this is not if you
take the oldest connected sum of S2 and
T2 you would get
um just the t2 in fact
this
resulting
surface is the connected sum of T2 and
T2 you can probably see right if you
have a taus on one side taus on another
side and you do the connected sum you
get this okay so it's not the same thing
however this is a good opportunity to
introduce a whole set of new a whole
class of new manifolds new surfaces
definition 16
so each time we connect some with a new
copy of T2 you get more and more Torah
you get more and more those um HS you
get more and more copies of Tash if you
like and we shall give it the name this
Sigma
subg is by
definition a lot of multiple copy
G copies of Taurus connected
some okay and this thing is called now
the name is not
felicitously chosen but we should call
it the rean
surface because in a certain context in
mathematics very important concept
context of algebraic geometry these
things are the Rema
surfaces of gen
G have you ever heard the word
genus well okay genus is a word of Latin
origin the plural is gener in French
it's it means kind or species and that's
why we use the word genus just learn the
word for this occasion genus G and the
picture is much easier to do you have a
c copy of T2 another copy of
T2 and then you just keep adding and the
connect St and copy of D2 so it looks
like
this as a matter of
convention we should like to decide what
Sigma of zero is what happens if we
don't have any copy well one school of
thought might say it's the empty set we
have nothing but it's more um practical
it turns out to decide that it is S2 two
dimensional sphere and also
note a much more natural convention that
or the result that Sigma 1 if you have
only one copy it is just equal to T2
itself
okay A little later today or maybe
tomorrow it will be useful to
have an alternative picture of Sigma g
reman surface of Gus
G here is the alternative
picture instead of having all those
donuts strong next to each other we are
going
to imagine that we have a big sphere in
might object that's not the sphere it
looks like an ellipsoid but that's okay
we are doing topology it's all soft and
then we are going to attach what the
professionals called
handles now I hope that you can you seen
the picture that I'm seeing because this
picture a little abstract is not
completely obvious to
everyone so this is supposed to
represent
another
picture for Sigma G is that you have
those G what we call
handles attached on a sphere